cat	menu_name	desc	order
basic	Physical/Vitals	"Physical measures and vitals represent a foundational category of health metrics that directly reflect an individual’s physiological state and lifestyle impact. These indicators—such as BMI, body fat percentage, waist circumference, and smoke pack years—offer insight into metabolic health and long-term disease risk. Functional assessments like grip strength and resting heart rate help quantify cardiovascular fitness and muscular integrity, while blood pressure serves as a critical marker of circulatory system status. Together, these metrics are often used in clinical, fitness, and preventative health contexts to monitor health status, guide interventions, and stratify risk."	1
lipid	Lipids	"A lipid panel is a standard blood test used to assess cardiovascular risk by measuring the levels of key blood lipids. It typically includes total cholesterol, LDL cholesterol (often labeled “bad” cholesterol), HDL cholesterol (“good” cholesterol), and triglycerides. These markers help evaluate how the body processes fats and can indicate risk for atherosclerosis, heart attack, and stroke. The lipid panel is a foundational tool in both routine screenings and the management of conditions like hyperlipidemia and metabolic syndrome. It is often used to guide lifestyle changes and pharmacologic interventions aimed at improving heart health."	2
cmp	Metabolic Panel	"A Comprehensive Metabolic Panel (CMP) is a commonly ordered blood test that provides a broad assessment of metabolic and organ function. It includes measurements of glucose, electrolytes (like sodium, potassium, and calcium), kidney markers (such as creatinine and BUN), and liver enzymes (such as ALT, AST, and ALP), as well as total protein and albumin levels. The CMP helps evaluate blood sugar regulation, electrolyte and fluid balance, and the health of the kidneys and liver. It is frequently used in routine checkups and to monitor conditions such as diabetes, hypertension, and liver or kidney disease."	3
adv	Advanced Biomarkers	"Advanced biomarkers refer to a category of blood-based indicators that extend beyond routine clinical panels and offer deeper insights into metabolic, hormonal, inflammatory, and cardiovascular health. These markers—such as CRP (inflammation), cystatin C (kidney function), SHBG and testosterone (hormonal status), Lp(a) and GGT (cardiometabolic risk), and vitamin D (bone and immune health)—are not typically included in standard screenings like a comprehensive metabolic panel (CMP) or basic lipid panel. They are often used in preventative, functional, or precision medicine contexts to identify subclinical dysfunctions or assess long-term disease risk. Their inclusion in testing strategies is growing as research supports their value in predicting outcomes and guiding early interventions."	4
cbc	CBC (Complete Blood Counts)	"A Complete Blood Count (CBC) panel is a standard clinical test that measures various components of the blood to assess overall health and detect a wide range of disorders. It includes key metrics such as red blood cell count, hemoglobin, hematocrit, white blood cell count, and platelet count, among others. These values help evaluate oxygen-carrying capacity, immune function, and clotting ability. The CBC is commonly used for diagnosing infections, anemia, inflammation, and hematologic conditions, and it serves as a routine part of health screenings and ongoing medical evaluations."	5
life	Lifestyle	"Lifestyle variables encompass self-reported behaviors related to diet and substance use that can significantly influence long-term health outcomes. This category includes specific dietary habits—such as intake of red meat, poultry, cheese, salt, and water—as well as patterns of alcohol consumption, including beer, wine, and spirits. These variables provide contextual insight into nutritional quality, hydration status, and potential exposures that may affect metabolic, cardiovascular, and overall health. While often overlooked in clinical settings, they are increasingly valued in personalized and preventive health approaches for their role in shaping disease risk and guiding lifestyle interventions."	6
meta	Metabolites	"Metabolites, as measured through NMR (nuclear magnetic resonance) metabolomics, represent a detailed profile of small molecules in the blood that reflect dynamic physiological processes. This category includes a wide range of biomarkers such as amino acids, lipoprotein subclasses, fatty acids, and glycolysis-related compounds that offer insight into energy balance, metabolic efficiency, and systemic health. Unlike traditional panels, NMR-based metabolomics enables high-resolution quantification of these molecules, providing a more nuanced view of cardiometabolic risk, inflammation, and metabolic flexibility. These advanced profiles are increasingly used in research and precision health to detect early pathophysiological changes and personalize interventions."	7
prot	Proteins	"Proteins, as measured by Olink’s platform, are quantified using proximity extension assays and reported in Normalized Protein eXpression (NPX) units, a relative measure that allows for high-throughput, multiplexed protein analysis. This category includes a wide array of circulating proteins involved in inflammation, cardiovascular function, neurology, oncology, and metabolic regulation. The NPX values reflect relative abundance within a study cohort rather than absolute concentrations, making them useful for identifying patterns and associations with disease risk across populations. These measurements are powerful for research and exploratory applications, helping to uncover protein-disease relationships, but are not intended for direct clinical interpretation or individualized assessment."	8
nutra	Nutraceuticals	"In our research, we examined correlations of reported uses of several products.  Our research is ongoing regarding these products and their impact on specific disease outcomes.  Below are early results of correlations and risk multipliers for several products and the categories in this guide. We continue to refine this work and will report additional findings soon. Nutraceuticals are the formulation of nutrients directed toward prevention and treatment of diseases (i.e. anemia, vitamin deficiencies), in addition to diet supplementation offering purported preventive health care choices for consumers. While the effects of many of these products on health and disease remain unclear, ongoing and future research will further shed light on their benefits and risks. Generally, nutraceuticals are not involved in clinical trials and approved by the FDA for statements related to improved health. For a comprehensive review please reference Nutrients, 2022 Nov 3;14(21):4637. https://www.mdpi.com/2072-6643/14/21/4637"	9